<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>architecture on Ketan Parmar (kpbird)</title>
    <link>http://kpbird.github.io/tags/architecture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in architecture on Ketan Parmar (kpbird)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; 2020. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://kpbird.github.io/tags/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Microservice Architecture: The Real Challenge</title>
      <link>http://kpbird.github.io/post/2019-06-21_microservice-architecture-the-real-challenge-c1561b619cd6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kpbird.github.io/post/2019-06-21_microservice-architecture-the-real-challenge-c1561b619cd6/</guid>
      <description>Microservice Architecture: The Real Challenge Microservice is a buzzword among the developer community. In this article, we will explore the most important points about Microservice architecture that are seldom addressed elsewhere. We will try to cover all the practical problems of moving to microservice architecture.
Let&amp;rsquo;s start with some advantages of microservice architecture. Following are three major advantage for which you may consider moving to microservice architecture.
 Engineering flexibility: Each service team can choose a different programming language or framework.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monolithic vs MicroService architecture</title>
      <link>http://kpbird.github.io/post/2015-09-23_monolithic-vs-microservice-architecture-5bf276e113cf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kpbird.github.io/post/2015-09-23_monolithic-vs-microservice-architecture-5bf276e113cf/</guid>
      <description>Monolithic architecture is something that build from single piece of material, historically from rock. Monolith term normally use for object made from single large piece of material. &amp;mdash; Non-Technical Definition Monolithic application has single code base with multiple modules. Modules are divided as either for business features or technical features. It has single build system which build entire application and/or dependency. It also has single executable or deployable binary &amp;mdash; Technical Definition Industry is using this approach since long to develop enterprise application.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
